DR. MANUEL MEYER | CURRICULUM VITæ

German (native), English (fluent), Swedish (proficient), Danish (basic), ▶ Languages:

French (basic), Spanish (basic)

▶ Identifiers: ORCID:0000-0002-0738-7581, INSPIRE HEP: Manuel.Meyer.1, Sco-

pus Researcher ID: 55463373300, Google Scholar



Research Interests

My interests lie in the field of astroparticle physics and experimental searches for dark matter, in particular in the form of axions and axion-like particles. My research has provided stringent limits on the coupling between photons and axion-like particles using astrophysical observations. I also participate in the characterization and commissioning of the transition edge sensor to be used in the ALPS II experiment and lead the development of machine-learning-based data analysis.

| >>> Experience | | |
|----------------|---|----------------------|
| Since 2023 | Associate Professor for Experimental Physics | Odense, Denmark |
| | ▶ Center for Cosmology and Particle Physics Phenomenology (CP3), University of | Southern Denmark |
| | ■ Group website | |
| 2021-2022 | Research group leader | Hamburg, Germany |
| | Institute for Experimental Physics, University of Hamburg | |
| | Parental leave: July 2021, March-July 2022 | |
| 2019 - 2021 | Marie Skłodowska-Curie Research Fellow | Erlangen, Germany |
| | ▶ Erlangen Center for Astroparticle Physics, University Erlangen-Nuremberg. Pl: | Prof. Stefan Funk |
| 2019 | Feodor Lynen Research Return Fellow | Hamburg, Germany |
| | Deutsches Elektron Synchrotron (DESY). Pl: Dr. Axel Lindner | |
| 2017 - 2019 | Feodor Lynen Research Fellow | Stanford, CA, USA |
| | Xavli Institute for Particle Astrophysics and Cosmology, Stanford University. Pl. ford | Prof. Roger Bland- |
| 2013 - 2016 | Post doctoral researcher | Stockholm, Sweden |
| | Oskar Klein Centre for Cosmoparticle Physics, Stockholm University. Pl: Prof. Ja | an Conrad |
| >>> Education | | |
| 2010 - 2013 | Ph.D., Physics, University of Hamburg | Hamburg, Germany |
| | Ph.D. thesis: The opacity of the Universe for high and very high energy γ -rays. Grade: "Magna Cum Laude" – with Honors Advisor: Prof. Dieter Horns | |
| 2004 - 2010 | Diploma in Physics, University of Hamburg | Hamburg, Germany |
| | Diploma thesis: Spectral Modeling of the Crab Nebula and Search for oscillato data induced by hidden Photons. <i>Grade: "Excellent, with Honors"</i> Advisor: Prof. Dieter Horns | ry features in X-ray |

>>> Selected Grants

| | Dr. Manuel Meyer · CV · ☑ mey@sdu.dk | |
|----------------|---|--------------------|
| 2021 | DFG Research Unit "Relativistic Jets in Active Galaxies" | Bonn, Germany |
| | Associated member of a research group funded by the German Research Foundation | ındation (DFG). |
| | Amount of funding: 3,600,000€ | |
| 2020 | ERC Starting Grant | Brussels, Belgium |
| | Research grant for early career scientists awarded by European Research Cou | uncil (ERC). |
| | Amount of funding: 1,441,000€ | |
| 2019 | Marie Skłodowska-Curie Research Fellowship | Brussels, Belgium |
| | Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions Research Fellowship awarded by the ERC. | |
| | Amount of funding: 175,000€ | |
| 2016 | Feodor Lynen Research Fellowship | Bonn, Germany |
| | Sponsorship for own research position from the German Humboldt Foundation | n. |
| | Amount of funding: 126,000€ | |
| >>> Awards | | |
| 2017 | Marie Skłodowska-Curie Actions Seal of Excellence | Brussels, Belgium |
| | Award for proposal submitted under the Horizon 2020 Marie Skłodowska-Cur | |
| | | |
| 2010 | Otto Stern Prize | Hamburg, Germany |
| | Prize for best diploma thesis in physics of the 2010 summer term at the University | ersity of Hamburg |
| >>> Collabor | ation Memberships | |
| since 2021 | Any Light Particle Search (ALPS) Collaboration | |
| SITICC LOLI | Leading the machine-learning-based data analysis development for the TES | detector: member |
| | of the executive board | |
| since 2013 | Fermi Gamma Ray Space Telescope Collaboration | |
| | ▶ Former coordinator of the dark matter and new physics working group | |
| since 2012 | Charankay Talasaana Array (CTA) Cansartium | |
| SINCE ZUIZ | Cherenkov Telescope Array (CTA) Consortium Former convener of the Dark Matter and Exotic Physics working group | |
| | Former convener of the Dark Matter and Exotic Physics working group | |
| since 2012 | High Energy Stereoscopic System (H.E.S.S.) Collaboration | |
| | Member of steering committee, former member of the executive and multi-v former deputy convener of the astroparticle working group | wavelength boards, |
| >>> Institutio | nal and Organizational Boards | |
| since 2023 | SDU Quantum Hub | Odense, Denmark |
| | ▶ Member of the steering committee | |
| | | |
| since 2023 | European COST Action CA21106 "Cosmic WISPers" | |
| | Danish country representative in management committee | |

>>> Selected Publications

since 2023

42 publications in peer-reviewed journals with major contribution (18 as corresponding author). Co-author of more than 65 publications of the H.E.S.S. collaboration, 25 publications of the Fermi-LAT collaboration, 28 confer-

Representative of the young science group leaders in the steering committee

Hamburg, Germany

Quantum Universe Excellence Cluster

ence proceedings, and 5 white papers. According to NASA ADS, the publications have in total more than 11,000 citations with an h index of 51. A publication list including all collaboration papers can be found on ORCID.

- 1. M. **Meyer** et al., A First Application of Machine and Deep Learning for Background Rejection in the ALPS II TES Detector, Annalen der Physik, Vol. 536, No. 1, 2200545 2024, arXiv: 2304.08406 [hep-ex]
- 2. C. Schwemmbauer et al. (including M. **Meyer**), *Direct dark matter searches using ALPS II's TES detection system*, PoS, Vol. EPS-HEP2023, p. 120, 2024
- 3. J. Rubiera Gimeno et al. (including M. **Meyer**), *A TES system for ALPS II Status and Prospects*, PoS, Vol. EPS-HEP2023, p. 567, 2024
- 4. J. Biteau and M. **Meyer**, *Gamma-Ray Cosmology and Tests of Fundamental Physics*, Galaxies, Vol. 10, No. 2, p. 39, 2022, arXiv: 2202.00523 [astro-ph.C0]
- 5. M. **Meyer** and T. Petrushevska, *Search for Axionlike-Particle-Induced Prompt* γ -Ray Emission from Extragalactic Core-Collapse Supernovae with the Fermi Large Area Telescope, Phys. Rev. Lett. Vol. 124, No. 23, 231101, p. 231101, 2020, arXiv: 2006.06722 [astro-ph.HE]

>>> Conference Contributions

Contributed to more than 25 conferences, workshops, and seminars (18 invited).

>> Selected Invited Presentations

| 2024 | TeV Particle Astrophysics Conference | USA |
|------|--|---------|
| 2024 | 15th International Workshop on the Identification of Dark Matter | Italy |
| 2023 | Cosmic magnetism in voids and filaments Conference | Italy |
| 2020 | Virtual Kashiwa Dark Matter Symposium 2020 | Japan |
| 2019 | 15th Patras Workshop on Axions, WIMPs, and WISPs | Germany |

>> Selected Contributed Presentations

| 2023 | European Physical Society Conference on High Energy Physics (EPS HEP) | Germany |
|------|---|---------|
| 2022 | 7th Heidelberg International Symposium on High-Energy Gamma- Ray Astronomy | Spain |
| 2019 | 1st CTA Symposium | Italy |
| 2018 | 8th International <i>Fermi</i> Symposium | USA |
| 2018 | TeV Particle Astrophysics 2018 | Germany |

>>> Supervision & Mentoring

| Fall 2024 Since 2023 | Current group: 1 PI, 4 post docs, 2 PhD students, 3 master students Mentor for the SDU Physics Mentoring program (currently 2 mentees) |
|-------------------------|---|
| Since 2021 | Mentor of the Fermi-LAT mentoring program (currently 1 mentee, 1 mentee in past cycle) |
| 2018-2022 | (Co-) Supervision of 3 PhD students: J. Davies (2020-2022), M. Crnogorčević (2018-2023), A. Yusafzai (2020-2022). |
| 2014-2023 | (Co-) Supervision of 3 master students, supervision of 5 bachelor students |

>>> Teaching and Formal Training in Teaching

>> Courses and Classes taught

| 2024 | Astroparticle Physics | Odense, Denmark |
|------|--|-----------------|
| | ▶ 5 ECTS lecture and exercise classes for master students, spring term 2024. | |
| 2024 | Electrodynamics | Odense, Denmark |

| | ▶ 5 ECTS lecture and exercise classes for undergraduate students, spring ter | m 2024. |
|-------------|--|-------------------------|
| 2023 - 2024 | Introduction to Quantum Mechanics | Odense, Denmark |
| | ▶ 5 ECTS lecture and exercise classes for undergraduate students, winter ter | rm 2023/2024. |
| 2023 - 2024 | Research Activities in Experimental Physics | Odense, Denmark |
| | 5 ECTS course project work on experimental physics and data analysis for sm students, winter term 2023/2024. | nall groups of graduate |
| 2021 - 2022 | Particle and Astroparticle Physics | Hamburg, Germany |
| | Seminars prepared by students in winter term 2021/2022. | |
| 2020 - 2022 | Gamma-ray Telescope in the Classroom | Erlangen, Germany |
| | Lectures, exercise classes, and observation nights for bachelors and mast term 2020/2021. | ters students in winter |
| 2019 - 2020 | Data Analysis II and Introduction to Machine Learning | Erlangen, Germany |
| | ▶ Lectures and exercise classes given for masters students in winter term 20 | 019/2020. |
| 2018 | Lectures for pre-collegiate students | Stanford, CA, USA |
| | Lectures given for high school students during particle physics and cosmo | logy summer courses. |
| 2011-2012 | Lab assistant for undergraduate physics students | Hamburg, Germany |
| | Supervision of small groups of students for week-long labs. Included teach back and grading. | ing, supervision, feed- |
| >> Training | | |
| 2018 | Stanford Scientific Teaching Summer Institute | Stanford, CA, USA |
| | ▶ Three day workshop on science-based teaching, inclusion, and equity. | |
| 2017 | Introduction to Undergraduate STEM Teaching | Stanford, CA, USA |
| | Online course offered by the Center for the Integration of Research Testemteachingcourse.org. Passed with distinction. | eaching and Learning, |

>>> Outreach

7 outreach talks for general public and high schools students, **7 articles for press releases, blogs, and newspapers**. Examples can be found here, here, here, here, here, here, here, here, and here. Also worked as a advisor for high school students at the DESY school labs (2008-2009).

| >>> Computer skills | |
|-------------------------|--|
| Operating systems: | Mac OS, Ubuntu, Windows |
| Programming languages: | python, Root, C++, C |
| ➤ Scientific Computing: | numpy, scipy, astropy, scikit-learn, iminuit, emcee, tensorflow & keras, matplotlib, hdf5, pandas, git |
| ▶ Developed Software: | gammaALPs, ebltable |
| ▶ Data analysis | Fermi-LAT (FERMIPY and Fermi Tools); H.E.S.S. and CTA (HAP and GAMMAPY); Swift XRT, NuSTAR, and XMM-Newton (pipelines and XSPEC); ALMA (CASA), ALPS II (TES) |
| ▶ Document preparation | LATEX, Keynote, OpenOffice, Microsoft Office |

>>> Reviewing

ical Journal C

- ▶ Member of scientific organizing committees
- Journal reviewer

Phystat gamma conference, International Cosmic Ray Conference (ICRC) 2021; "Recontres du Vietnam: Very High Energy Phenomena in the Universe" 2018 conference; "The puzzle of dark matter 2018" conference Physical Review Letters, Physical Review D, Astrophysical Journal (ApJ), the Journal of Cosmology and Astroparticle Physics (JCAP), Physics Letters B, Monthly Notes of the Royal Astronomical Society (MNRAS), European Phys-